<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
   <teiHeader>
      <fileDesc>
         <titleStmt>
            <title>God save the King A sermon preached in St. Pauls Church the 27th. of March 1639. Being the day of his Maiesties most happy inauguration, and of his northerne expedition. By Henry Valentine, D.D.</title>
            <author>Valentine, Henry, d. 1643.</author>
         </titleStmt>
         <editionStmt>
            <edition>
               <date>1639</date>
            </edition>
         </editionStmt>
         <extent>Approx. 66 KB of XML-encoded text transcribed from 22 1-bit group-IV TIFF page images.</extent>
         <publicationStmt>
            <publisher>Text Creation Partnership,</publisher>
            <pubPlace>Ann Arbor, MI ; Oxford (UK) :</pubPlace>
            <date when="2012-10">2012-10 (EEBO-TCP Phase 2).</date>
            <idno type="DLPS">A14262</idno>
            <idno type="STC">STC 24575</idno>
            <idno type="STC">ESTC S103273</idno>
            <idno type="EEBO-CITATION">99839030</idno>
            <idno type="PROQUEST">99839030</idno>
            <idno type="VID">3424</idno>
            <availability>
               <p>To the extent possible under law, the Text Creation Partnership has waived all copyright and related or neighboring rights to this keyboarded and encoded edition of the work described above, according to the terms of the CC0 1.0 Public Domain Dedication (http://creativecommons.org/publicdomain/zero/1.0/). This waiver does not extend to any page images or other supplementary files associated with this work, which may be protected by copyright or other license restrictions. Please go to https://www.textcreationpartnership.org/ for more information about the project.</p>
            </availability>
         </publicationStmt>
         <seriesStmt>
            <title>Early English books online.</title>
         </seriesStmt>
         <notesStmt>
            <note>(EEBO-TCP ; phase 2, no. A14262)</note>
            <note>Transcribed from: (Early English Books Online ; image set 3424)</note>
            <note>Images scanned from microfilm: (Early English books, 1475-1640 ; 1223:14)</note>
         </notesStmt>
         <sourceDesc>
            <biblFull>
               <titleStmt>
                  <title>God save the King A sermon preached in St. Pauls Church the 27th. of March 1639. Being the day of his Maiesties most happy inauguration, and of his northerne expedition. By Henry Valentine, D.D.</title>
                  <author>Valentine, Henry, d. 1643.</author>
               </titleStmt>
               <extent>[2], 36 p.   </extent>
               <publicationStmt>
                  <publisher>Printed by M. F[lesher] for John Marriott; and are to be sold at his shop in St. Dunstans Church-yard in Fleet-streete,</publisher>
                  <pubPlace>London :</pubPlace>
                  <date>1639.</date>
               </publicationStmt>
               <notesStmt>
                  <note>Printer's name from STC.</note>
                  <note>Reproduction of the original in the Yale University. Library.</note>
               </notesStmt>
            </biblFull>
         </sourceDesc>
      </fileDesc>
      <encodingDesc>
         <projectDesc>
            <p>Created by converting TCP files to TEI P5 using tcp2tei.xsl,
      TEI @ Oxford.
      </p>
         </projectDesc>
         <editorialDecl>
            <p>EEBO-TCP is a partnership between the Universities of Michigan and Oxford and the publisher ProQuest to create accurately transcribed and encoded texts based on the image sets published by ProQuest via their Early English Books Online (EEBO) database (http://eebo.chadwyck.com). The general aim of EEBO-TCP is to encode one copy (usually the first edition) of every monographic English-language title published between 1473 and 1700 available in EEBO.</p>
            <p>EEBO-TCP aimed to produce large quantities of textual data within the usual project restraints of time and funding, and therefore chose to create diplomatic transcriptions (as opposed to critical editions) with light-touch, mainly structural encoding based on the Text Encoding Initiative (http://www.tei-c.org).</p>
            <p>The EEBO-TCP project was divided into two phases. The 25,368 texts created during Phase 1 of the project (2000-2009), initially available only to institutions that contributed to their creation, were released into the public domain on 1 January 2015. The approximately 40,000 texts produced during Phase 2 (2009- ), of which 34,963 had been released as of 2020, originally similarly restricted, were similarly freed from all restrictions on 1 August 2020. As of that date anyone is free to take and use these texts for any purpose (modify them, annotate them, distribute them, etc.). But we do respectfully request that due credit and attribution be given to their original source.</p>
            <p>Users should be aware of the process of creating the TCP texts, and therefore of any assumptions that can be made about the data.</p>
            <p>Text selection was based on the New Cambridge Bibliography of English Literature (NCBEL). If an author (or for an anonymous work, the title) appears in NCBEL, then their works are eligible for inclusion. Selection was intended to range over a wide variety of subject areas, to reflect the true nature of the print record of the period. In general, first editions of a works in English were prioritized, although there are a number of works in other languages, notably Latin and Welsh, included and sometimes a second or later edition of a work was chosen if there was a compelling reason to do so.</p>
            <p>Image sets were sent to external keying companies for transcription and basic encoding. Quality assurance was then carried out by editorial teams in Oxford and Michigan. 5% (or 5 pages, whichever is the greater) of each text was proofread for accuracy and those which did not meet QA standards were returned to the keyers to be redone. After proofreading, the encoding was enhanced and/or corrected and characters marked as illegible were corrected where possible up to a limit of 100 instances per text. Any remaining illegibles were encoded as &lt;gap&gt;s. Understanding these processes should make clear that, while the overall quality of TCP data is very good, some errors will remain and some readable characters will be marked as illegible. Users should bear in mind that in all likelihood such instances will never have been looked at by a TCP editor.</p>
            <p>The texts were encoded and linked to page images in accordance with level 4 of the TEI in Libraries guidelines.</p>
            <p>Copies of the texts have been issued variously as SGML (TCP schema; ASCII text with mnemonic sdata character entities); displayable XML (TCP schema; characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or text strings within braces); or lossless XML (TEI P5, characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or TEI g elements).</p>
            <p>Keying and markup guidelines are available at the <ref target="http://www.textcreationpartnership.org/docs/.">Text Creation Partnership web site</ref>.</p>
         </editorialDecl>
         <listPrefixDef>
            <prefixDef ident="tcp"
                       matchPattern="([0-9\-]+):([0-9IVX]+)"
                       replacementPattern="http://eebo.chadwyck.com/downloadtiff?vid=$1&amp;page=$2"/>
            <prefixDef ident="char"
                       matchPattern="(.+)"
                       replacementPattern="https://raw.githubusercontent.com/textcreationpartnership/Texts/master/tcpchars.xml#$1"/>
         </listPrefixDef>
      </encodingDesc>
      <profileDesc>
         <langUsage>
            <language ident="eng">eng</language>
         </langUsage>
         <textClass>
            <keywords scheme="http://authorities.loc.gov/">
               <term>Charles --  I, --  King of England, 1600-1649 --  Early works to 1800.</term>
               <term>Sermons, English --  17th century.</term>
            </keywords>
         </textClass>
      </profileDesc>
      <revisionDesc>
         <change>
            <date>2011-12</date>
            <label>TCP</label>Assigned for keying and markup</change>
         <change>
            <date>2011-12</date>
            <label>SPi Global</label>Keyed and coded from ProQuest page images</change>
         <change>
            <date>2012-02</date>
            <label>Amanda Flynn</label>Sampled and proofread</change>
         <change>
            <date>2012-02</date>
            <label>Amanda Flynn</label>Text and markup reviewed and edited</change>
         <change>
            <date>2012-05</date>
            <label>pfs</label>Batch review (QC) and XML conversion</change>
      </revisionDesc>
   </teiHeader>
   <text xml:lang="eng">
      <front>
         <div type="title_page">
            <pb facs="tcp:3424:1" rendition="simple:additions"/>
            <pb facs="tcp:3424:1" rendition="simple:additions"/>
            <p>God ſave the King. A SERMON PREACHED IN S<hi rend="sup">t</hi>. <hi>PA<g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>LS</hi> CHVRCH the 27<hi rend="sup">th</hi>. of March. 1639. <hi>BEING</hi> THE DAY OF HIS MAIESTIES MOST happy Inauguration, and of His Northerne Expedition. BY HENRY VALENTINE, D.D.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>LONDON,</hi> Printed by <hi>M. F.</hi> for JOHN MARRIOTT; and are to be ſold at his Shop in S<hi rend="sup">t</hi>. <hi>Dunſtans</hi> Church<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>yard in Fleet-ſtreete. 1639.</p>
         </div>
      </front>
      <body>
         <div type="sermon">
            <pb facs="tcp:3424:2"/>
            <pb n="1" facs="tcp:3424:2"/>
            <head>God ſave the King.</head>
            <epigraph>
               <q>
                  <bibl>
                     <hi>1 SAM. 10.24.</hi>
                  </bibl>
                  <p>And all the people ſhouted, and ſaid, God ſave the King.</p>
               </q>
            </epigraph>
            <p>
               <seg rend="decorInit">T</seg>He Text is <hi>verbum diei in die ſue;</hi> and a word ſpoken in due ſeaſon is like apples of gold in pictures of ſilver. This is the <hi>Kings</hi> Day, and this is the <hi>Kings</hi> Text; and I will uſe the words of a <hi>King</hi> for my Introduction: <hi>My heart hath indited a good matter, and I will ſpeake of the things which I have made touching the King.</hi> God make my tongue the pen of a ready writer, and tune your tongues to the <hi>Duty</hi> of the Day, and <hi>Ditty</hi> of the Text, which is, <hi>God ſave the King: And all the people ſhouted, and ſaid, God ſave the King.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>The Text preſents you with two faire pieces.</p>
            <milestone type="tcpmilestone" unit="unspecified" n="1"/>
            <p>Firſt, the <hi>Acclamation</hi> of the people, <hi>And all
<pb n="2" facs="tcp:3424:3"/>the people ſhouted;</hi> and this I call <hi>Vox populi,</hi> the <hi>Voice</hi> of the people.</p>
            <p>
               <milestone type="tcpmilestone" unit="unspecified" n="2"/> Secondly, the <hi>Apprecation</hi> of the people; it was not <hi>Vox &amp; praeterea nihil,</hi> voice and nothing elſe, as we ſay of the Nightingale; but as they ſhouted, ſo they ſaid ſomething, and what was it? <hi>God ſave the King;</hi> and this I call <hi>Votum populi,</hi> the <hi>Vote</hi> of the people.</p>
            <p>In the firſt of theſe, three things are obſervable.</p>
            <p n="1">1. The <hi>ground</hi> and <hi>occaſion</hi> of their joy, They had a <hi>King,</hi> that was one: and ſuch a <hi>King</hi> as the like was not among the people, that was another. Both expreſſed in the beginning of the Verſe.</p>
            <p n="2">2. The <hi>greatneſſe</hi> and <hi>vehemency</hi> of their joy. They did not <hi>gaudere in ſinu,</hi> their breaſts were too narrow to containe it; but like <hi>Iordan</hi> in the time of Harveſt, it overflowes the bankes, and breakes out at their lips, ſo that heaven and earth rings, and reſounds with the ecchoes of it, for they <hi>ſhouted.</hi>
            </p>
            <p n="3">3. The <hi>generality,</hi> and <hi>univerſality</hi> of their joy. The young men did not ſhout, and the old men weep, as at the building of the ſecond Tem<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ple; but <hi>all</hi> the people ſhouted, the Quire is full, the joy univerſall.</p>
            <p>In the ſecond, that is, the <hi>Apprecation</hi> of the people, two things are conſiderable.</p>
            <p n="1">1. Their <hi>Fa<gap reason="illegible" resp="#OXF" extent="1+ letters">
                     <desc>•…</desc>
                  </gap>,</hi> they prayed for the King. For as he that prayeth not at all cannot be a good <hi>man;</hi> ſo he that prayeth not for the <hi>King,</hi> cannot be a good <hi>Subject.</hi>
            </p>
            <p n="2">2. Their <hi>Forme</hi> of prayer, <hi>God ſave the King.</hi>
               <pb n="3" facs="tcp:3424:3"/>For they knew that if <hi>God</hi> did not ſave their <hi>King,</hi> their <hi>King</hi> could not ſave them out of the hands of their enemies.</p>
            <p>Theſe are the ſeverall parts of the Text, where<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>in at this time I ſhall exerciſe your patience and attention: and firſt of the grounds, and occaſions of their joy; They had a <hi>King,</hi> and ſuch a <hi>King</hi> as the like was not among all the people, and hence their ſhouting and ovations. <hi>And all the peo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ple ſhouted, and ſaid, God ſave the King.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <milestone type="tcpmilestone" unit="unspecified" n="1"/> The firſt ground of their joy was that they had a <hi>King. Governours</hi> they had, <hi>Captaines</hi> they had, <hi>Iudges</hi> they had, but a <hi>King</hi> they had not till now; and now they have him, they rejoyce in him, for they ſhouted.</p>
            <p>Shouting is an expreſſion of joy, and joy is a paſſion and affection of the mind, arifing from the <hi>ſenſe</hi> and <hi>preſence</hi> of ſome good. And that <hi>Kings</hi> are to be ranked in this <hi>Predicament,</hi> and inrolled in the number of Good Things, is moſt manifeſt from that promiſe which God made unto <hi>Abra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ham: I will</hi> (ſayes God) <hi>make thee exceeding fruit<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>full,</hi>
               <note place="margin">Geneſ. 17.6.</note> 
               <hi>I will make Nations of thee, and Kings ſhall come out of thee.</hi> In which promiſe you may ob<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſerve as it were three degrees of Compariſon. Firſt, God promiſes that he ſhould be a <hi>Father;</hi> then, that he ſhould be a Father of <hi>Nations;</hi> then, a Father of <hi>Kings,</hi> which is the ſuperlative Bleſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſing, and the very Crowne and Creſt of the Pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>miſe.</p>
            <p>Againe, God is good, and ſo are all things that come from him; now <hi>there is no power but of God,</hi>
               <pb n="4" facs="tcp:3424:4"/>ſayes the <hi>Apoſtle:</hi> and how is it of him? not by way of <hi>permiſsion,</hi> but of <hi>commiſsion;</hi> not by way of <hi>Deficiency,</hi> but of <hi>Efficiency;</hi> not by way of <hi>ſufferance,</hi>
               <note place="margin">Rom 13.1.</note> but of <hi>ordinance:</hi> for <hi>the powers that are, are ordained of God, and whoſoever reſiſteth the power,</hi>
               <note place="margin">Inde illis po<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>teſtas, unde ſpi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ritus. <hi>Tertul. Apol. 30</hi> Cujus juſſu na<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſcuntur homines, ejus juſſu conſti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tuuntur Princi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pes. <hi>Iren.</hi>
               </note> 
               <hi>reſiſteth the Ordinance of God.</hi> Thence have they their <hi>power,</hi> from whence they have their <hi>ſpirit,</hi> ſayes <hi>Tertul.</hi> And he that made them <hi>men,</hi> makes them <hi>Princes,</hi> and that after the ſame man<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ner, ſayes <hi>Irenaeus.</hi> Hence is it that their <hi>Crowne</hi> is ſaid to be Gods, their <hi>Scepter</hi> Gods, their <hi>Throne</hi> Gods, their <hi>anointing</hi> Gods: for he is the Maſter of the <hi>ſubſtance,</hi> whoſoever be the Maſter of the <hi>Ceremony.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>I confeſſe that the children of Iſrael are char<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ged by <hi>Samuel</hi> to have committed <hi>grande malum,</hi>
               <note place="margin">1 Sam. 12.17.</note> a great evill in asking a <hi>King,</hi> and God atteſted it by thunder from heaven. The truth is, they did not aske <hi>malum,</hi> a thing in its ſelfe, and ſimply evill; but they asked <hi>Bonum malè,</hi> a good thing in an ill manner; For they asked a <hi>King</hi> to the prejudice, and apparent injurie of Father <hi>Samuel;</hi> they asked him out of wantonneſſe, and pride of heart, that they might be like unto other Nations; and they were reſolved to have a <hi>King,</hi> whether God and his Prophet would or no.<note place="margin">
                  <hi>Vide Abulens: in locum. Et</hi> La<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>timers 5. Serm. before <hi>K.</hi> Edw.</note> Nay (ſay they) but we will have a King. Now if <hi>malum</hi> be <hi>ex quolibet defectu,</hi> this muſt needs be <hi>grande malum,</hi> that had ſo many defects in it, though the thing they aſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ked was <hi>Grande bonum,</hi> a great bleſſing and a precious treaſure, as <hi>Latimer</hi> calls it, and it will appeare by theſe particulars to be ſo.</p>
            <pb n="5" facs="tcp:3424:4"/>
            <p n="1">1. A King is <hi>Decus Iſraelis,</hi> the <hi>Beauty,</hi> and <hi>Ornament</hi> of <hi>Iſrael:</hi> when <hi>Saul</hi> was ſlain,<note place="margin">2 Sam. 1.19.</note> 
               <hi>David</hi> lamented over him with this Lamentation, The <hi>Beauty</hi> of <hi>Iſrael</hi> is ſlain upon thy high places. For the <hi>King</hi> is the Fountain of <hi>Government,</hi> Govern<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment of <hi>Order,</hi> and Order of <hi>Beauty;</hi> ſo that a <hi>King</hi> governing his people with good and juſt Lawes, makes the Common-wealth a <hi>Naomi,</hi> and the excellency of Beauty, which otherwiſe would be but <hi>rudis indigeſta<expan>
                     <am>
                        <g ref="char:abque"/>
                     </am>
                     <ex>que</ex>
                  </expan> moles, &amp; monſtrum infor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>me;</hi> A maſſe of <hi>confuſion,</hi> and ugly and deformed <hi>Monſter.</hi>
            </p>
            <p n="2">2. A King is <hi>Lucerna Iſraelis,</hi> the <hi>Light and Lamp of Iſrael.</hi>
               <note place="margin">2 Sam. 21.17.</note> 
               <hi>David</hi> being reſcued from a great danger, the people ſwore that he ſhould goe no more out with them to battle, leſt the <hi>Light</hi> of <hi>Iſrael</hi> ſhould bee quenched. The <hi>King</hi> by his <hi>Lawes,</hi> as the <hi>Sun</hi> by his <hi>Beames,</hi> diſpels and ſcat<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ters thoſe deeds of Darkneſſe which otherwiſe would cover the face of the Common-wealth: ſo that his ſubjects live in <hi>Goſhen</hi> and have light in their dwellings; and the light is good, for he that made it, ſaid it: and if there be any that rejoyces not in this Light, I dare ſay his deeds are evill.</p>
            <p n="3">3. A King is <hi>Imago Dei,</hi> the bright <hi>Image</hi> of God, and the moſt magnificent and conſpicuous repreſentation of the Divine Majeſty;<note place="margin">Nec alio animo rectorem ſuum intuetur, quam ſi Dii immorta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>les poteſtatem vi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſendi ſui faciant. <hi>Senec. l. 1. de clem. cap. 20.</hi>
               </note> and wee joy in the <hi>Pictures</hi> of our friends, when we can<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>not behold their <hi>Perſons.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>All Governours (ſayes <hi>Greg. Naz.</hi>) are Gods <hi>Pictures.</hi> Inferiour and ſubordinate Magiſtrates are halfe pieces drawne from the head to the
<pb n="6" facs="tcp:3424:5"/>ſhoulders, or middle; but <hi>Kings</hi> are the Pictures of God at length, and repreſent him in ſuch due proportions, that as <hi>God</hi> is our <hi>inviſible King,</hi> ſo the <hi>King</hi> is our <hi>viſible God.</hi> One hath ſaid it that cannot flatter, <hi>Dixi Dii eſtis, I have ſaid ye are gods,</hi> and if he have ſaid it, we may ſay it after him.</p>
            <p n="4">
               <milestone type="tcpmilestone" unit="unspecified" n="4"/> 4. A King is <hi>Paſtor populi,</hi> the <hi>Shepheard</hi> of the <hi>people,</hi> ſo <hi>Cyrus</hi> is called, and ſo <hi>David</hi> whom God tooke from feeding of ſheep, to feed <hi>Iacob</hi> his peo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ple, and <hi>Iſrael</hi> his inheritance. And no expreſſion more frequent in profane Authors. The people then that have no King are like a flock of <hi>ſheepe</hi> that have no <hi>ſhepheard;</hi> and <hi>ſheepe</hi> that have no <hi>ſhepheard</hi> will be <hi>ſcattered:</hi>
               <note place="margin">1 King. 22.17.</note> 
               <hi>I ſaw</hi> (ſayes the Pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>phet) <hi>all Iſrael ſcattered upon the hils as ſheepe that have no ſhepheard.</hi> And ſheepe that are <hi>ſcattered</hi> are eaſily devoured, according to that of <hi>Ezech. They were ſcattered becauſe they had no ſhepheard,</hi>
               <note place="margin">Ezech. 34.5.</note> 
               <hi>and they became meat unto all the beaſts of the field when they were ſcattered.</hi> So then with a <hi>King</hi> we are <hi>Oves paſcuae,</hi> ſheepe of the Paſture feeding by ſtill waters: but without a King we are <hi>Oves occi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſionis, ſheep</hi> of the <hi>ſhambles,</hi> and appointed to bee ſlaine. And therefore good reaſon that we ſhould heare the voice of our <hi>ſhepheard,</hi> and rejoyce in him when he goes in and out before us.</p>
            <p>
               <milestone type="tcpmilestone" unit="unspecified" n="5"/> Laſtly, Kings are called <gap reason="foreign" resp="#OXF">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap> 
               <hi>Benefactours,</hi> according to that of our Saviour,<note place="margin">Luke 22.25.</note> The <hi>Kings</hi> of the Gentiles exerciſe Lordſhip over them, and they that exerciſe authority upon them are called <hi>Benefactours.</hi> And if we look into the Catalogue of the Aegyptian Kings, wee ſhall finde two of
<pb n="7" facs="tcp:3424:5"/>them ſo ſirnamed. And well may the King bee called a <hi>Benefactour,</hi> for he is the Miniſter of God to thee for <hi>good,</hi> (ſayes the Apoſtle.) He conſerves thy life and body which is thy <hi>naturall</hi> good; hee cheriſhes vertue, and puniſhes vice, which is thy <hi>morall</hi> good; he ſecures thy eſtate and poſſeſſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ons, which is thy <hi>civill</hi> good; he defends the faith, and maintaines Gods true Religion, and worſhip, which is thy <hi>ſpirituall</hi> good. So that <gap reason="foreign" resp="#OXF">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap>, A <hi>King</hi> is the beſt <hi>Benefactour,</hi> and the greateſt friend we have upon earth; for we may ſay of him as <hi>Solomon</hi> did of wiſdome, when he comes, all good things what<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſoever come together with him.</p>
            <p>Now recollect and lay all theſe together, that a <hi>King</hi> is the <hi>Beauty</hi> of a Nation, the <hi>Light</hi> of the Common-wealth, the <hi>Image</hi> of God, the <hi>Paſtour</hi> of his people, and the beſt <hi>Benefactour</hi> to his ſub<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>jects; and we cannot but acknowledge that the oyle of annointing is <hi>Oleum laetitiae,</hi> the oyle of <hi>gladneſſe.</hi> For I dare ſay, that next to <hi>Chriſtus Do<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>minus</hi> the Lord Chriſt, <hi>Chriſtus Domini</hi> the Lords annointed is to be preferred in our mirth as the chiefe of our joy, and the <hi>Crowne</hi> of our rejoyce<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing. And therfore the children of <hi>Iſrael</hi> had good reaſon to be joyfull in their <hi>King,</hi> eſpecially in ſuch a <hi>King</hi> as the like was not among all the peo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ple, and that is the other ground and occaſion of their rejoycing.</p>
            <p>
               <milestone type="tcpmilestone" unit="unspecified" n="2"/> 
               <hi>Solomon,</hi> the moſt glorious King that ever wore a Crowne, or bare a Scepter,<note place="margin">Wiſd. 7.1, 2, 3.</note> confeſſes that hee was but <hi>Mortalis</hi> a mortall, and <hi>ſimilis omnibus</hi> like
<pb n="8" facs="tcp:3424:6"/>unto all; conceived alike, borne alike, nurſed a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>like, and there is no <hi>King</hi> (ſayes he) that is other<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wiſe. There are a generation of men in the world which like the frogs in Egypt ſwarme in Kings Chambers, who poyſon unwary Princes with the breath of flattery, blowing them up with mon<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtrous and prodigious conceits of a ſuppoſed <hi>Di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vinity.</hi> If <hi>Alexander</hi> be victorious, he hath them about him will ſay and ſweare too that hee is the ſon of <hi>Iupiter,</hi> and decree him divine honours. If <hi>Demitian</hi> ſend out a Decree,<note place="margin">Mart.</note> it is <hi>Edictum Demini Dei<expan>
                     <am>
                        <g ref="char:abque"/>
                     </am>
                     <ex>que</ex>
                  </expan> noſtri:</hi> If <hi>Herod</hi> ſit on the Throne and make an elegant Oration, it is the voice of God and not of man. And when once the ſpirit of <hi>Princes</hi> is in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fected with this poyſon, they thinke they may thunder with <hi>Iupiter,</hi> and command the Sea, For
<q>
                  <l>— Quid credere de ſe</l>
                  <l>Non poſsit,<note place="margin">Juven.</note> cum laudatur Diis aequapoteſtas:</l>
               </q> The truth is, that he that ſits upon the <hi>Throne</hi> is but a man, and <gap reason="foreign" resp="#OXF">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap>, ſubject to the ſame paſſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ons that others are, and <hi>Morietur ſicut home,</hi> hee ſhall dye like a man, and his pompe ſhall not fol<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>low him: ſo that the difference betwixt <hi>Saul</hi> and the reſt of the people is not to be ſought for in his naturall <hi>principles,</hi> or eſſentiall <hi>properties:</hi> but ei<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther in the <hi>Ornaments</hi> of his <hi>Body,</hi> or in the <hi>endow<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ments</hi> and <hi>accompliſhments</hi> of his minde, or in both.</p>
            <p>
               <milestone type="tcpmilestone" unit="unspecified" n="1"/> As for the <hi>ornaments</hi> of his <hi>body,</hi> there was none like him among all the children of <hi>Iſrael,</hi> for he was a goodly perſon, and from his ſhoulders upward higher then any of the people.</p>
            <pb n="9" facs="tcp:3424:6"/>
            <p>It pleaſed the wiſdome of God to make choice of ſuch an one for his firſt <hi>King,</hi> that the <hi>eminence</hi> of his <hi>ſtature,</hi> and <hi>procerity</hi> of his <hi>perſon</hi> might ſpeake him <hi>Dignum imperio,</hi> and conciliate reve<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rence, and obedience from the people. <hi>Xenophon</hi> reports of the <hi>Lacedemonians</hi> that they fined their King <hi>Archidamus</hi> becauſe he maried a little wo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>man, fearing leaſt they ſhould have <gap reason="foreign" resp="#OXF">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap>, not <hi>Kings</hi> but <hi>Kinglings;</hi> which might prove a blemiſh to their State, and a diminution to Majeſty.</p>
            <p>When <hi>Samuel</hi> was ſent to anoint one of the ſons of <hi>Ieſſe,</hi> no ſooner did he ſee <hi>Eliab</hi> the eldeſt, but he concluded that the Lords anointed was before him, and the reaſon was, becauſe he looked upon his <hi>countenance,</hi> and the <hi>height</hi> of his ſtature.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Pliny</hi> reports of the Bees,<note place="margin">Nat. Hiſt. lib. 11. cap. 16, 17. <hi>Inſignis regis forma eſt, diſſimi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>liſ<expan>
                        <am>
                           <g ref="char:abque"/>
                        </am>
                        <ex>que</ex>
                     </expan> caeter is tum magnitudine, tum nitore.</hi> Sen. l. 1. de clement. cap. 19.</note> that <hi>eſſe uti<expan>
                     <am>
                        <g ref="char:abque"/>
                     </am>
                     <ex>que</ex>
                  </expan> ſine Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ge non poſſunt,</hi> they cannot be without a King: yet the Bee which they chooſe is <hi>duplo caeter is major,</hi> twice as big as any of the other.</p>
            <p>Or it may be God made choice of ſuch an one, that the <hi>eminency</hi> of his <hi>ſtature</hi> might be an <hi>Em<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bleme</hi> of the <hi>ſoveraignty</hi> and <hi>ſupremacy</hi> of his <hi>office. Kings</hi> in the Scripture are called the <hi>Higher pow<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ers,</hi> the <hi>Heads</hi> of the <hi>Tribes,</hi> the children of the moſt <hi>High,</hi> the high <hi>Hills,</hi> and tall <hi>Cedars.</hi> A <hi>King</hi> (ſayes <hi>Tertull:</hi>) is <hi>à Deo primus, poſt Deum ſecundus:</hi> count not God, and he is the firſt; count God, and he is the ſecond. Honour the King (ſayes <hi>Ignat:</hi>) for there is nothing more great,<note place="margin">Ep. ad Smyrn.</note> or excellent <gap reason="foreign" resp="#OXF">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap>, in all created nature.</p>
            <p>So then the <hi>Prieſt,</hi> yea though he be the <hi>high-Prieſt</hi>
               <pb n="8" facs="tcp:3424:7"/>
               <gap reason="duplicate" extent="1 page">
                  <desc>〈1 page duplicate〉</desc>
               </gap>
               <pb n="9" facs="tcp:3424:7"/>
               <gap reason="duplicate" extent="1 page">
                  <desc>〈1 page duplicate〉</desc>
               </gap>
               <pb n="10" facs="tcp:3424:8"/>muſt not meaſure with the <hi>King,</hi> or thinke to hold up his head as high as his <hi>Soveraigne. A<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bimelech</hi> was high-Prieſt,<note place="margin">1 Sam. 22.15.</note> yet confeſſes himſelfe twice in one verſe to be <hi>Sauls</hi> ſervant. <hi>Abiathar</hi> was high Prieſt, yet <hi>Solomon</hi> depoſed him, and in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>veſted <hi>Zadok</hi> with his office. To ſee a <hi>Biſhop</hi> tread upon the neck of an <hi>Emperour,</hi> and mount his <hi>Steed</hi> whilſt a <hi>King</hi> holds his <hi>ſtirrop,</hi> are as prodi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gious and portentuous ſpectacles as the <hi>Eclypſes</hi> of the great Luminaries of heaven.</p>
            <p>S. <hi>Bernard</hi> writing to an <hi>Archbiſhop</hi> in <hi>France,</hi>
               <note place="margin">Siomnis anima, &amp; veſtra: quis ves excepit ab u<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>niverſit te? ſi quis tentat exci<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pere, tentat deci<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pare. <hi>Bern. Epiſt. 42. Acts 25.10.</hi>
               </note> preſſes him with <hi>omnis anima,</hi> let every ſoule bee ſubject, and if every ſoule, then yours, for he that goes about to exempt you, does but deceive you.</p>
            <p>S. <hi>Paul</hi> that great <hi>Doctor</hi> of the Gentiles ſtands at <hi>Caeſars</hi> Judgement ſeate, where <gap reason="foreign" resp="#OXF">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap>, I ought (ſayes he) to be judged, and ſubmit my ſelf to his ſentence.</p>
            <p>Nay, <hi>Chriſt</hi> himſelfe, the <hi>High-Prieſt</hi> of our profeſſion, and great <hi>Biſhop</hi> of our ſoules paid tri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bute unto <hi>Caeſar,</hi> and acknowledged the power of <hi>Pilate</hi> a ſubordinate Miniſter to be given from Heaven.</p>
            <p>And ſurely if the Doctrine of the <hi>Conclave</hi> which advances the <hi>Miter</hi> above the <hi>Crown</hi> bee new and nought: that of the <hi>Conſiſtory</hi> cannot bee good, for it advances the <hi>Thiſtle</hi> above the <hi>Cedar,</hi> the people above the Prince, witneſſe theſe, and the like dangerous and ſeditious poſitions. <hi>Popu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lus Rege eſt praeſtantior, &amp; melior,</hi> the <hi>people</hi> are better than the <hi>King,</hi>
               <note place="margin">Lib de jure regni.</note> and of greater authority. The collective body hath the ſame power over
<pb n="11" facs="tcp:3424:8"/>the King, that the <hi>King</hi> hath over any one perſon. The people may arraigne their <hi>Prince,</hi> and the Miniſters excommunicate him; ſo far <hi>Buchanan.</hi> And another of the ſame ſtamp affirmes that the power of the people over the King, is the ſame that the power of a generall <hi>Councell</hi> is over the <hi>Pope,</hi> and as the <hi>Councell</hi> may diſplace the one if he be an <hi>Heretique,</hi> ſo the people may depoſe the o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther if he be a <hi>Tyrant</hi>
               <note n="*" place="margin">And a Ty<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rant he is (ſayes another of them) if hee hinder the bringing in of their diſci<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pline.</note>. Thus <hi>Herod</hi> and <hi>Pilate,</hi> mortall enemies, become ſworne brothers in per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſecuting the Lords anointed, and like <hi>Sampſons</hi> foxes though they look contrary wayes, yet are joyned by the tailes, and both carry the firebrands of ſedition. But returne we againe to <hi>Saul</hi> who was not ſo eminent for the ſtature of his body, as he was for the <hi>gifts,</hi> and <hi>accompliſhments</hi> of his <hi>minde,</hi> for in this reſpect alſo there was none like him among all the people.</p>
            <p>
               <milestone type="tcpmilestone" unit="unspecified" n="2"/> The <hi>vulgar</hi> latine reades it <hi>non erat vir melior illo,</hi> there was not a better then he among all the children of Iſrael. A <hi>Senuiſti,</hi> was objected againſt <hi>Samuel,</hi> a <hi>David</hi> as yet was too yong to come in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>to competition with him. Or as <hi>Abulen:</hi> ſatisfies the doubt, <hi>perſona loquens intelligitur excepta,</hi> the perſon ſpeaking which was <hi>Samuel,</hi> muſt be exce<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pted from the compariſon.</p>
            <p>When our Saviour <hi>Chriſt</hi> gave this honourable teſtimony of <hi>Iohn</hi> the <hi>Baptiſt,</hi> that among them that were born of women there was not a greater then he, it is manifeſt that <hi>Chriſt</hi> himſelf was ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cepted, for <hi>Iohn</hi> was not worthy to looſe the latchet of his ſhooe.</p>
            <pb n="12" facs="tcp:3424:9"/>
            <p>The <hi>ordinary gloſſe</hi> ſayes that <hi>Saul</hi> at the time of his election was in <hi>ſtatu praeſentis juſtitiae,</hi> in the ſtate of preſent righteouſneſſe. <hi>Lyra</hi> ſayes that he was not only <hi>vir bonus,</hi> but <hi>excellentis bonitatis,</hi> a good man, but of excellent, and exemplary good<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſſe. S. <hi>Bernard</hi> ſpeaking of perſeverance ſayes that <hi>bonus erat Saul, &amp; optimus: ſed cecidit, &amp; re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>probus factus eſt, Saul</hi> was a good man, yea the beſt in <hi>Iſrael,</hi> but he fell away and became a re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>probate.</p>
            <p>As for <hi>humility,</hi> the Scripture gives him this te<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtimony, that he was <hi>parvulus in oculis ſuis,</hi> little in his owne eyes. And <hi>magna &amp; rara virtus honora<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ta humilitas, humility</hi> in robes is a rare and admi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rable vertue.</p>
            <p>As for <hi>piety,</hi> no ſooner was he inveſted with the Kingdome but he accompanies <hi>Samuel</hi> unto <hi>Gilgal,</hi> and there ſacrifices peace offerings unto the Lord. And ſo zealous was he of the Law of God that he would not ſuffer a witch to live.</p>
            <p>As for <hi>Clemency,</hi> he would not ſuffer thoſe ſons of <hi>Belial</hi> to be put to death who deſpiſed him in their hearts, and ſaid, ſhall <hi>Saul</hi> raigne over us?</p>
            <p>This was <hi>Saul;</hi> but to reſume the words of S. <hi>Bernard, Cecidit, cecidit,</hi> he fell, he fell: His <hi>humility</hi> degenerated into <hi>pride:</hi> his <hi>piety</hi> into <hi>profaneneſſe,</hi> his <hi>clemency</hi> into <hi>cruelty,</hi> for he that ſpared the ſons of <hi>Belial,</hi> did not ſpare the <hi>Prieſts</hi> of the <hi>Lord.</hi> Let him therefore that ſtandeth take heed left he fall, and whoſoever thou art, worke out thy ſalvation with feare and trembling, and be not high-minded but feare. Looke upon <hi>Saul</hi> in
<pb n="13" facs="tcp:3424:9"/>the New <hi>Teſtament,</hi> and thou wilt not deſpaire; looke upon <hi>Saul</hi> in the Old <hi>Teſtament,</hi> and thou wilt not preſume: The one of the chiefeſt <hi>ſinner</hi> became a <hi>Saint,</hi> and the other of the <hi>beſt</hi> man in Iſrael became a <hi>reprobate.</hi> And ſo we diſcharge the firſt <hi>circumſtance,</hi> the ground and occaſion of their joy, they had a <hi>King,</hi> and ſuch a <hi>King</hi> as both in reſpect of the <hi>ornaments</hi> of his <hi>body,</hi> and the <hi>indowments</hi> of his <hi>minde</hi> there was none like him among all the people, and come to the ſecond <hi>circumſtance,</hi> which is the <hi>greatneſſe</hi> and <hi>vehemen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cy</hi> of their joy, they ſhouted. <hi>And all the people ſhouted, and ſaid, God ſave the</hi> King.</p>
            <p>
               <milestone type="tcpmilestone" unit="unspecified" n="2"/> Joy is a paſſion which ſpreads, and dilates, and inlarges the heart, and if the impreſſions thereof be ſtrong and maſculine, it cannot containe it ſelf, but breakes out into ſenſible expreſſions. As ſometimes into <hi>laughing,</hi> ſo did <hi>Sarahs</hi> joy at the tidings of a Son; ſometimes into <hi>ſinging,</hi> ſo did the Angels joy at the birth of our Saviour; ſome<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>times into <hi>ſhouting,</hi> ſo did the peoples joy at the inauguration of their King, and this of all other is the loudeſt, and ſhrilleſt accent of jubilation.<note place="margin">1 King. 1.40.</note> At the Coronation of King <hi>Solomon the people rejoyced with great joy, ſo that the earth</hi> (ſayes the Text) <hi>rent with the ſound of them.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>It fareth with Kings as with all other bleſſings, <hi>carende magis quam fruendo,</hi> their worth and ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cellency is better knowne by wanting, then ha<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ving them.</p>
            <p>We reade in the book of <hi>Iudges</hi> that there was no <hi>King</hi> in <hi>Iſrael,</hi> and how went the ſquares then?
<pb n="14" facs="tcp:3424:10"/>why every man did that which was right in his own eyes. And what was that? <hi>Micah</hi> a private man ſets up an Idoll, and conſecrates a Prieſt. <hi>Gibeah</hi> a City raviſhes a woman to death. <hi>Dan</hi> a Tribe fals to robbing of houſes, &amp; cutting of Throates. <hi>Families, Cities,</hi> and <hi>Tribes</hi> all out of courſe, and no ſoundneſſe at all in the body po<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>litique.</p>
            <p>The cauſe of all which diſorder was the want of ſome body: Not of a <hi>Prieſt</hi> to teach them, but of a <hi>King</hi> to governe them. A <hi>Prieſt</hi> there was in Iſrael, but a <hi>King</hi> there was not, and hence it was that every one did that which was right in his <hi>owne</hi> eyes, and no body did that which was right in <hi>Gods</hi> eyes.</p>
            <p>God be thanked, a bad <hi>King</hi> is a Thing which the oldeſt man here cannot remember, yet let me tell you that <hi>Tyranny</hi> is rather to be choſen then <hi>Anarchie,</hi> and <hi>praeſtat ſub malo principe eſſe quam nullo,</hi> better a bad King then no King at all, ſayes <hi>Tacitus.</hi> Better it is to feare <hi>one</hi> then <hi>many,</hi> better one <hi>Lion,</hi> then all the <hi>Beares,</hi> and <hi>Bores,</hi> and wilde <hi>beaſts</hi> of the Forreſt. If the Trees cannot prevaile with the <hi>Vine,</hi> or <hi>Olive</hi> to be their King, yet a King they will have though it be but the <hi>Bramble.</hi> I gave them ſayes God a King in my <hi>anger,</hi> and tooke him away in my <hi>wrath.</hi> A bad <hi>King</hi> is the teſtimony of Gods anger, but no King at all an ar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gument of his wrath, and indignation; and wrath is the dregs, and lees of the cup, anger but the top of it.</p>
            <p>So then, the greatneſſe of the evill which re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dounds
<pb n="15" facs="tcp:3424:10"/>to a Nation by the want of a <hi>King,</hi> ſuffi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ciently commends the greatneſſe of the bleſſing, and great bleſſings muſt be entertained with ſuta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ble affections. It was truly ſaid of <hi>Balaam</hi> a falſe Prophet, that the <hi>ſhout</hi> of a King was amongſt them, for all other expreſſions are too low, and flat for it.</p>
            <p>But theſe latter times have produced a genera<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion of Vipers called Anabaptiſts, who inſtead of rejoycing in their King, raile at him, and their de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>viſe is only how they may caſt him downe whom God hath exalted: for they affirme as impudent<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly, as ignorantly, that <hi>Chriſtian liberty</hi> makes the office of a Magiſtrate utterly <hi>unlawfull,</hi> and Euan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gelicall <hi>perfection</hi> makes it altogether uſeleſſe and ſuperfluous: and if it be unlawfull it is not a bleſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſing, but a curſe; if uſeleſſe, not a benefit, but a burthen.</p>
            <p>There is I confeſſe a glorious priviledge pur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>chaſed for us by the death of Chriſt, which wee call <hi>Chriſtian liberty,</hi> but it conſiſts only in a free<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dome from the <hi>ceremonies,</hi> the <hi>curſe,</hi> and <hi>rigour</hi> of the Law, the <hi>power</hi> of Satan, and <hi>dominion</hi> of ſin; not in a freedome from the <hi>Doctrine</hi> and <hi>O<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bedience</hi> of the Morall Law, or the yoke of lawfull <hi>authority, Civill,</hi> or <hi>Eccleſiaſticall.</hi> For they that ſo underſtand it, and apply it (ſayes S. <hi>Peter</hi>) uſe their liberty for a cloake of maliciouſneſſe. And S. <hi>Paul</hi> tels us that though we be called to liberty,<note place="margin">Gol. 5.13.</note> 
               <hi>yet we muſt not uſe our liberty for an occaſion to the fleſh.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>As for Evangelicall <hi>perfection,</hi> in their ſenſe it
<pb n="16" facs="tcp:3424:11"/>is but an <hi>Idea,</hi> a <hi>dreame,</hi> a meere <hi>chimaera.</hi> For good and bad, wheate and chaffe are mingled to<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gether in the floore, and <hi>ſic fuit ab initio,</hi> thus it was from the beginning, and thus it will be unto the end, till Chriſt come with his fan in his hand and thorowly purge his floore. They that are good are but <hi>imperfectly</hi> good, and ſo long as the fleſh luſteth againſt the Spirit, and the law of the members fights againſt the law of the minde, of<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fences muſt needs come; and Chriſtians may do things puniſhable by the civill Magiſtrate. <hi>Moſes</hi> the Magiſtrate of Gods owne people had need have a rod in his hand, and he ſhall meete with thoſe in the congregation that deſerve to be beat with it: Elſe S. <hi>Paul</hi> had ſaid in vaine (writing to Chriſtians) <hi>ſi male egeris,</hi> if thou doeſt that which is evill be afraid. And S. <hi>Peters</hi> exhortation had been to no purpoſe;<note place="margin">1. Pet. 4.17.</note> 
               <hi>Let none of you ſuffer as a murtherer, or as a thiefe, or as an evill doer, or as a buſie-body in other mens matters.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <hi>Sergius Paulus</hi> when he was converted to the Faith; did not abjure his authority as a thing Anti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>chriſtian. <hi>Cornelius</hi> was made a Chriſtian, yet ceaſed not to be a Centurion. The <hi>Eunuch</hi> was baptized, yet did not relinquiſh his office and au<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thority under the Queen of the <hi>Aethiopians Chriſt</hi> and <hi>Caeſar</hi> may dwell together; we may give un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>to <hi>God</hi> the things that are <hi>Gods,</hi> and yet give unto <hi>Caeſar</hi> the things that are <hi>Caeſars;</hi> we may feare God, and yet honour the King; and as they ſin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ned that ſaid we will have no King but <hi>Caeſar,</hi> ſo doe they alſo that ſay, we will have no King but
<pb n="17" facs="tcp:3424:11"/>Chriſt, no law but that of the Spirit. And there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore S. <hi>Peter</hi> hath marked thoſe out to be chiefly reſerved to the day of Judgement to be puniſhed,<note place="margin">1 Pet. 2.10.</note> who deſpiſe ſo great a bleſſing as Government.</p>
            <p>For <hi>Non minor eſt uſus Magiſtratus quàm panis, aquae, ſolis, &amp; aeris;</hi> Magiſtracy is no leſſe need<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>full and neceſſary amongſt men then bread and water, the ſun and the ayre, ſayes M. <hi>Calvin.</hi>
               <note place="margin">Inſt. l. 4. c. 20.</note> All which are bleſſings ſo great, and generall, that men cannot live without them but by Miracle, which brings me to the third circumſtance, the generality and univerſality of their joy, <hi>All ſhouted.</hi>
            </p>
            <p n="3">
               <milestone type="tcpmilestone" unit="unspecified" n="3"/> 3. Fit it was that an univerſall benefit ſhould be entertained with an univerſall joy. A King is <hi>commune bonum,</hi> a common good; and good the more common it is, the better it is; and the bet<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter it is the more joy it occaſions. The Magiſtrate (ſayes S. <hi>Paul</hi>) is the Miniſter of God to thee for good, to thee whoſoever thou art. To thee No<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bleman, to thee Churchman, to thee Gentleman, to thee Tradeſman, to thee Husbandman, to thee Merchant, to thee Mariner.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Seneca</hi> tels <hi>Nero, Anima Reipublicae tu es,</hi>
               <note place="margin">Lib. 1. de Clem.</note> 
               <hi>illa corpus tuum;</hi> thou art the ſoule of the Common<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wealth, and the Commonwealth is thy Body. Now the ſoule is <hi>tota in toto, &amp; tota in qualibet parte,</hi> whole in the whole body, and whole in e<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>very part of it: Even ſo the King inanimates and informes the whole collective body of the peo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ple, and every particular man of it, of what degree, quality, or profeſſion ſoever, ſo that to ſay wee have no part in <hi>David</hi> is the voice of a rebell;
<pb n="18" facs="tcp:3424:12"/>for yong men and maids, old men and children have all a part in him, and profit by him.</p>
            <p>Againe, as a King is the ſoule, ſo alſo he is the Sun of the Common-wealth, according to that of the Pſalmiſt,<note place="margin">Pſal. 89.36.</note> 
               <hi>His Throne ſhall be as the Sun.</hi> The Sun is <hi>Sponſus naturae,</hi> the beauty and Bridegroom of Nature, appointed by God to rule the Day, and it runs from one end of the Heavens unto the other, ſo that nothing is hid from the heate and light of it, but every creature from the Cedar to the Shrub receives benigne and propitious influ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ences from it: ſo a King (as before I told you) is <hi>Decus Iſraelis,</hi> the beauty of Iſrael, the ſupreame Magiſtrate, the effects and influences of whoſe go<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vernment, as peace, juſtice, and religion extend o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ver the whole Kingdome, and reach from <hi>Dan</hi> even to <hi>Beerſheba,</hi> from <hi>Aarons</hi> head to the ſkirts of his cloathing; ſo that high and low, rich and poore, one with another, and all together owe their <hi>bene eſſe</hi> unto him.</p>
            <p>And for this cauſe (it may be) amongſt many others, Kings were of old Crowned neare ſome Fountaine, becauſe they are Fountaines and com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mon bleſſings, the ſtreames of whoſe government do glad the City of God, and refreſh his inheri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tance. For <hi>Rogis vigilia omnium domos, illius la<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bor omnium etia, illius induſtria omnium delicias, illius occupatio omnium vacationem tuetur,</hi> When the King watches we may all ſleep, when he la<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bours we may all reſt, his Terme is our Vacation, and when he workes every man may keep holy day.</p>
            <pb n="19" facs="tcp:3424:12"/>
            <p>And now when I looke upon this congregati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on of Iſrael, I cannot but breake out into the words of the <hi>Pſalmiſt, Ecce quàm bonum, &amp; quàm jucundum,</hi> behold how good and pleaſant a thing it was to ſee ſo many men of one minde, and one mouth! for all ſhouted, and all ſaid the ſame thing, <hi>Gaudium omnium gaudium ſingulorum, &amp; gaudium ſingulorum gaudium omnium.</hi> The joy of all was the joy of every one, and the joy of every one the joy of all. Thus it is in heaven, and thus it was here, and I would to God it was thus in all places.</p>
            <p>But oh the ſtrife of tongues! Oh the great thoughts and diviſions of heart that are amongſt us! Contempt of Authority is become the cha<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>racter of a Chriſtian, the cognizance of a ſincere profeſſor; libelling and ſpeaking evill of dignities the language and dialect of God people; preach<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing Obedience to the Magiſtrate civill, and Eccle<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſiaſticall, is interpreted downe right flattery, and gaping after preferment. Prejudice &amp; faction hath ſo ſhuffled and confounded all things, that a man can come into no pariſh, nor congregation but he ſhall finde ſome Mutes, ſome but halfe Vowels, ſome not doing their duty at all, others doing it ſo faintly, that a man may perceive their hearts are not right in this matter.</p>
            <p>Well fare this Congregation of Iſrael, <hi>Mens omnibus una, &amp; vox omnibus una,</hi> they were all of one minde, and one mouth; they all thought the ſame thing, and ſpake the ſame thing; every one in the Quire was a loud Cymball, for all ſhout<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed; and a well tuned Cymball too, for all prayed;
<pb n="20" facs="tcp:3424:13"/>which brings me to the ſecond part of the Text; the <hi>Vote</hi> and <hi>Apprecation</hi> of the people:
<q>And all the people, &amp;c.</q>
            </p>
            <p>Firſt, I exhort (ſayes the Apoſtle) that ſuppli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cations, and prayers, and interceſſions, and giving of thankes be made for all men, and firſt for Kings, and ſuch as be in Authority. And what manner of <hi>Kings</hi> were there in thoſe dayes? Idolaters, Infidels, Tyrants, Perſecutors, thoſe of whom <hi>David</hi> long before had propheſied;<note place="margin">Pſal. 2.2.</note> The <hi>Kings</hi> of the earth have ſet themſelves, and the Rulers take counſell againſt the Lord, and his an<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nointed. <hi>Nero</hi> the Romane Emperour, and ſu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>preame Magiſtrate was a Lion, ſo S. <hi>Paul</hi> cals him; he was <hi>Dedicator damnationis noſtrae,</hi> the firſt that drew out the ſword of perſecution, ſo <hi>Tertull.</hi> He was ſo profligately, and deſperately wicked and tyrannicall, that many thought hee ſhould riſe againe,<note place="margin">Lib. 20. de civ. Dei cap. 19.</note> and be that <hi>Antichriſt</hi> and man of ſin which was to be revealed, ſo S. <hi>Auguſt.</hi> and yet as bad as he was, S. <hi>Paul</hi> enjoynes prayers for him, and ſo does S. <hi>Peter</hi> for the Emperour <hi>Clau<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dius</hi> one not much better. For <hi>Suetonius</hi> reports of him that he was ſo mercileſſe, and given to bloodſhed that he would have tortures, and pu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>niſhments executed in his owne preſence, and de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lighted to looke upon the faces of Fencers as they lay gaſping, and yeelding up their laſt breath; be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſides he was a man inordinately given to the wan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ton love of women; yet for all this the Chriſti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ans of thoſe times muſt <hi>honour</hi> him. And this theſe
<pb n="21" facs="tcp:3424:13"/>bleſſed <hi>Apoſtles</hi> did not to curry favour with the Emperours, or to flatter themſelves into prefer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment, but to copie out their Maſters leſſon, and to ſhew that they were his Diſciples, who ſaid, Pray for them that perſecute you. And that this was the conſtant practice of the Primitive Church, <hi>Iuſtin Martyr</hi> in his <hi>Apol.</hi> 2. <hi>Origen</hi> in his 8. booke <hi>cont. Celſum. Arnob.</hi> in his 3. booke <hi>cont. Gentes. Tertull.</hi> in his <hi>Apol.</hi> 30. beſides the ancient Liturgies, are my witneſſes.</p>
            <p>Of all Chriſtian duties <hi>Prayer</hi> is the beſt; the Apoſtle hath given it the chiefe ſeate, and ſet it at the upper end of the Table. And of all kinde of prayers <hi>Interceſsion</hi> is the beſt; for neceſſity (ſayes <hi>Chryſoſt:</hi>) enforces us to pray for our ſelves, but charity invites us to pray for others. And chari<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ty is that which gives a tincture, and relliſh to all our prayers, for without it the tongues of men and Angels are but as ſounding braſſe, and a tinkling Cymball. And ſurely the beſt kinde of Interceſſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on is that which is made for the <hi>beſt,</hi> namely, for <hi>Kings,</hi> and ſuch as be in <hi>Authority.</hi> Hence is it that our Mother the <hi>Church</hi> of <hi>England</hi> is ſo co<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pious in it. For in her <hi>Liturgie</hi> ſhe prayes for the King foure or five ſeverall times, and yet I dare ſay commits no Tautologie, or idle repetition. For his ſeverall capacities as a <hi>man,</hi> as a <hi>Chriſtian,</hi> as a <hi>Magiſtrate,</hi> as the <hi>Supreme</hi> Magiſtrate, upon whom lyeth the care of the Church and Com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mon-wealth, require it of us. Thoſe then that doe curtaile divine Service as <hi>Hanun</hi> did the gar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ments of <hi>Davids</hi> Ambaſſadours, and uſe the
<pb n="22" facs="tcp:3424:14"/>prayers of the Church as a noiſe of Muſique at a Play to entertaine the company till the Actors be ready, are not only diſobedient to the Church in not obſerving her order, but injurious alſo to the King in depriving him of the benefit of thoſe prayers which the Church hath appointed for him. And this is no ſmall injury, for <hi>Preces ſubdi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>torum vires Regum,</hi> the prayers of the people are the power of the King: Kings are the heads of the people, but the prayers of the people are thoſe locks of haire wherein their ſtrength principally conſiſteth.</p>
            <p>Sure I am that none ſtand ſo much in need of prayers as <hi>Kings,</hi> and ſuch as be in <hi>Authority.</hi> For ſuch is the weight and multitude of their imploy<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ments; that many times they cannot pray for themſelves. Well might S. <hi>Ambroſe</hi> wonder at <hi>Davids ſepties in die,</hi> ſeaven times a day doe I praiſe thee, and make this inference upon it: <hi>Si David ſepties regni licèt neceſsitatibus occupatus, &amp;c.</hi> If <hi>David</hi> notwithſtanding the affaires of a Kingdome could doe it ſeaven times, private men may doe it ſeaventy times ſeaven.</p>
            <p>But beſides this, <hi>Kings</hi> and ſuch as are in <hi>Au<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thority</hi> are moſt aſſaulted with temptations. That which Chriſt ſaid of his Diſciples is true of <hi>Kings, Satanas appetiit vos,</hi> Satan deſires to have you, and like the King of <hi>Syria</hi> bends his power eſpecially againſt the King of Iſrael. So that were it not that <hi>cor Regis in manu Domini,</hi> the heart of the King was in the hands of the Lord, I ſhould wonder with S. <hi>Chryſoſtome</hi> if any of the Rulers could bee
<pb n="23" facs="tcp:3424:14"/>ſaved. For the devill opens his envenomed Qui<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ver, and ſhootes all his fiery darts at ſuch perſons, as well knowing that <hi>Regis ad exemplum,</hi> the ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ample of a King brings vice into faſhion, and gan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>grenes the whole body. For ſayes <hi>Siracides,</hi>
               <note place="margin">Eccleſ. 10.2.</note> As the Judge of the people is himſelfe, ſo are his of<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ficers; and what manner of man the Ruler of the City is, ſuch are they that dwell therein. For the people like <hi>Iacobs</hi> ſheepe conceive by the eye, and like the inferiour <hi>Orbes</hi> follow the motion of the <hi>primum mobile,</hi> contrary to their owne naturall inclinations. If <hi>Ieroboam</hi> ſin he makes Iſrael ſin too, and if he ſet up Calves at <hi>Dan</hi> and <hi>Bethel,</hi> all <hi>Iſrael</hi> will be ſuch Calves as to goe up and wor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſhip them.</p>
            <p>But ſuppoſe <hi>Kings</hi> ſtood not in need of our prayers, yet ſure I am <hi>we</hi> our ſelves ſtand in need to pray for them, for as <hi>Iacobs</hi> life was bound up in the life of <hi>Benjamin,</hi> ſo is the good of the <hi>ſubject</hi> in the proſperity of the <hi>Prince.</hi> Hence the <hi>Iewes</hi> were commanded to pray for the life of <hi>Nebu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>chadnezzar,</hi> and the peace of <hi>Babylon,</hi> becauſe in the peace thereof they ſhould have peace. And S. <hi>Paul</hi> exhorting us to pray for <hi>Kings</hi> and ſuch as be in <hi>Authority,</hi> drawes his motive <hi>ab utili,</hi> for by this meanes we ſhall live a quiet and a peacea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ble life in all godlineſſe and honeſty. <hi>Kings</hi> and <hi>Queenes</hi> are nurſing Fathers, and nurſing Mothers, and if the nurſe be ill, the childe that ſuckes the breaſt cannot thrive and proſper. Nay the Lords anointed is <hi>Spiramentum nariam,</hi>
               <note place="margin">Lam. 4.20.</note> the breath of our noſtrils; ſtop and extinguiſh that, and death enſues
<pb n="24" facs="tcp:3424:15"/>immediately. So that in praying for Kings wee pray for our ſelves, our prayers returne into our owne boſomes, for the bleſſings powred upon them like the oyntment powred on the head of <hi>Aaron</hi> ſtayes not there, but runs downe to the beard, yea to the very ſkirts of the cloathing. Or as the raine falls firſt upon the hils, but ſtayes not there, but deſcends into the vallies from whoſe vapours at firſt it was engendred. When the ſons of <hi>Iacob</hi> went into <hi>Egypt</hi> to fetch corne for their Father, did they not fetch it for themſelves &amp; their Families? When the members of the body feed the belly, doe they not feed themſelves, and pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vide for their owne nouriſhment? When we pray for the <hi>King,</hi> what doe we elſe but pray for our ſelves, and provide for the welfare of our owne Families and poſterities, for under his ſhadow we live, and like the ivie cannot grow without his ſupportance?<note place="margin">Acts 12.20.</note> So that as they of <hi>Tyre</hi> and <hi>Sidon</hi> ſaw a neceſſity of making a peace with King <hi>Herod</hi> becauſe their Countrey was nouriſhed by the Kings Countrey: So a neceſſity of praying for the <hi>King</hi> lyes upon every one of us, not only be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cauſe <hi>Dominus opus habet;</hi> but becauſe we our ſelves have need of it, for our welfare is nouriſhed by the Kings welfare, our honour by the Kings honour, our peace by the Kings peace, our ſafety by the Kings ſafety, and therefore God ſave the King, which is the Forme of their prayer, and the laſt circumſtance in the Text. <hi>And all the people ſhouted, and ſaid, God ſave the King.</hi>
            </p>
            <pb n="25" facs="tcp:3424:15" rendition="simple:additions"/>
            <p n="2">2. <hi>Pineda</hi> obſerves that it was the cuſtome of all Nations at the inauguration of their Kings,<note place="margin">Lib. 2. de reb. Salom. cap. 6.</note> to uſe ſolemne Apprecations, <hi>boni ominis ergô.</hi> As ſometimes <hi>foeliciter,</hi> ſometimes <hi>De noſtris annis tibi Iupiter augeat annos.</hi> Sometimes <hi>Auguſto foe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>licior, Trajano probior.</hi> Sometimes <hi>Dii te ſervent,</hi> and the like: all which (ſayes he) were doubtleſſe derived from this ſacred and ancient form in the Text, <hi>Vivat Rex,</hi> let the King live, for ſo it is in the Hebrew, and the Septuagint renders it, <gap reason="foreign" resp="#OXF">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap>, and our old Engliſh Bible reades it, God lend the King life; and no forme of Apprecation more full, or fit then this. For the bleſſing of <hi>life,</hi> is the <hi>life</hi> of all <hi>bleſsings,</hi> it being the foundation of whatſoever we have or hope for. Hence <hi>pellem pro pelle,</hi> skin for skin, and all that ever a man hath will he give for his life, and a living <hi>dog</hi> is better then a dead <hi>Lion.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>And as none more full, ſo none more fit; for <hi>Vita omnium brevis, Regum plerum<expan>
                     <am>
                        <g ref="char:abque"/>
                     </am>
                     <ex>que</ex>
                  </expan> breviſsima,</hi> the lives of all men are ſhort, but the lives of Kings for the moſt part ſhorteſt. It was a King that com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>plained, <hi>My ſoule is continually in my hands;</hi>
               <note place="margin">Pſal. 119.109.</note> and in another place, <hi>Feare is on every ſide, for they take counſell together againſt me, and deviſe how they may take away my life. Darius</hi> did wiſely to allow money for the building of the Temple,<note place="margin">Ezra 6.9, 10.</note> and bul<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lockes and rams for the burnt offerings, that ſo the <hi>Iewes</hi> might offer ſacrifices of ſweet ſavour unto the God of heaven, and pray for the life of the King, and of his ſons. If we reflect and look back upon former ages, wee ſhall finde <hi>Shimeis</hi> and
<pb n="26" facs="tcp:3424:16"/>
               <hi>Shebai, Abſaloms</hi> and <hi>Achitophels, Tereſhes,</hi> and <hi>Bigthans,</hi> all ſons of <hi>Belial</hi> flying in the face of ſa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cred Majeſty, and ſeeking to lay violent hands up<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on the Lords <hi>Anointed.</hi> And howſoever theſe ſpirits were once well laid, and walked not in the <hi>Primitive Church,</hi> yet in theſe latter times they have beene conjured up by the ſeditious Doctrine of the <hi>Ieſuites,</hi> and are become familiar ſpirits in all parts of Chriſtendome. <hi>Haec eſt ſalutaris medi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tatio</hi> ſayes <hi>Mariana,</hi> this is a wholeſome medita<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion for Kings next their heart, to thinke, <hi>ſe eâ con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ditione vivere,</hi> that they live in that caſe and con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dition, <hi>ut non ſolum jure, ſed cum laude &amp; gloria perimi poſsint,</hi> that they may not only be ſlaine lawfully, but to the praiſe and glory of them that doe it. And I would to God this was the doctrine of the <hi>Ieſuites</hi> only, for we know the men, and we know their communication; but this leaven hath ſpread further, and even ſowred them that take upon them to bee reformers of the reformed Churches. And whereas <hi>Mariana</hi> ſayes it may be done <hi>cum laude, Buchanan</hi> goes further, and would have it done <hi>cum praemio</hi> too. For if I (ſayes he) had power to make a law, I would award re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>compence to be given for killing of <hi>Tyrants,</hi> as men uſe to reward them for their paines who kill wolves or beares, and deſtroy their yong ones. Surely (beloved) this Doctrine deſerves to be the <hi>Inprimis</hi> in the blacke Catalogue of the Doctrine of the devils, it is the doctrine of <hi>Beelzebub</hi> the Prince of devils, it is the <hi>bane</hi> of mens ſoules, the <hi>blemiſh</hi> of Chriſtian religion, and the <hi>breach</hi> of all
<pb n="27" facs="tcp:3424:16"/>common tranquillity. And is it not high time to pray for the lives of <hi>Kings,</hi> when ambition, envie, faction, and all diſcontented humors are thus clapt on the back, and ſet on to offer violence to their perſons whom God would have accounted ſacred and inviolable, and hath therefore hedged them in as he did the Tree in the Garden, with a <hi>nolite tangere,</hi> touch them not? <hi>Saul</hi> was a barba<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rous Tyrant, for he hunted the life, and ſought af<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter the ſoule of <hi>David</hi> who was moſt faithfull a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mong all his ſervants; he commanded <hi>Doeg</hi> to fall upon the Prieſts of the Lord, and to ſlay foureſcore and five perſons which did weare a linnen <hi>Ephod;</hi> and not ſatisfied therewith, com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mands him further to ſmite <hi>Nob</hi> the Citie of the Prieſts, both man and woman, childe and ſuckling, oxe and aſſe with the edge of the ſword. Beſides, he neglected the care of Gods publique Worſhip and Service, for the Arke of God was not enqui<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>red at in the dayes of <hi>Saul;</hi> beſides he was rejected of God, and <hi>traditus Satanae,</hi> delivered into the actuall poſſeſſion of the devill; yet notwithſtand<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing all this, yea notwithſtanding a concurrence of all deſirable circumſtances of opportunity, yea, notwithſtanding <hi>David</hi> was the man that was <hi>an<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nointed</hi> by <hi>Samuel,</hi> and <hi>appointed</hi> by God to the Kingdome, yet he durſt not lay his hands upon the Lords anointed, but reverenced the <hi>Vnction,</hi> and ſpared his <hi>enemy,</hi> ſaying, <hi>Who can lay hands up<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on the Lords anointed and be guiltleſſe?</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <hi>Rodolph</hi> Duke of <hi>Suevia</hi> endeavouring to take away the Empire from <hi>Henry</hi> the Fourth, whom
<pb n="28" facs="tcp:3424:17"/>
               <hi>Hildebrand</hi> had excommunicated, loſt his right hand in the battle, and being ready to breath out his diſtreſſed ſoule, looking on the ſtumpe of his arme and fetching a deep ſigh, he ſaid to the Bi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſhops that were about him, behold this is the hand wherewith I did ſweare allegiance to my Sove<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>raigne Lord <hi>Henry.</hi> And therefore <hi>Vivat Rex,</hi> let the King live, be he an Infidel, an Heretique, a Tyrant, an Apoſtate, a Perſecutor, or depoſed and excommunicate by the Pope, for none of all theſe can unlooſe the bonds of allegiance, evacu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ate Gods ordinance, or cut in ſunder the ſinewes of the ſubjects obedience.</p>
            <p>But becauſe,<note place="margin">Mart.</note> as the Poet ſayes truly, <hi>Noneſt vi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vere, ſed valere, vita;</hi> this apprecation muſt reach further than a bare life, and ſimple ſubſiſtence; namely, to the health of his body, the quiet of his mind, the proſperity of his affaires, the ſucceſſe of his government, the victory of his Armies: and the Hebrew word is of that latitude to beare it, and the <hi>Caldee</hi> paraphraſes it, Let the King live, <hi>i.e. Sit Rex foelix, cedant omnia regi foelicitèr,</hi> Let the King live happy, let all things ſucceede fortunately, and whatſoever hee doth let it pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſper. Then <hi>Solomon</hi> lived indeed when he ſate not onely in the Throne of God,<note place="margin">1 Chron. 29.23</note> as King in ſtead of <hi>David</hi> his Father, but <hi>proſpered,</hi> and all Iſrael obeyed him.<note place="margin">Apolog. 30.</note> And <hi>Tertullian</hi> is my witneſſe, that the <hi>Primitive</hi> Chriſtians prayed not onely for the life of the Emperour, but for his <hi>happineſſe</hi> and <hi>proſperity</hi> alſo. His words are theſe; we wiſh the Emperour a long life, a ſecure Empire, valiant ar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mies,
<pb n="29" facs="tcp:3424:17"/>a faithfull Councell, a loyall people, a quiet government; <hi>Et quaecun<expan>
                     <am>
                        <g ref="char:abque"/>
                     </am>
                     <ex>que</ex>
                  </expan> Hominis &amp; Caeſaris vo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ta ſunt;</hi> whatſoever good things elſe, either Man or Caeſar can deſire. And who was this Empe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rour for whom they thus prayed? It was <hi>Severus,</hi> for in his time (ſayes St. <hi>Ierome</hi>) <hi>Tertullian</hi> flouri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>riſhed; and <hi>Severus</hi> was an Infidel, a Tyrant, and the author of the fifth perſecution, and yet they wiſh him proſperity in the name of the Lord. And if it was thus done for the <hi>dry</hi> tree, what ſhall be done for the <hi>greene?</hi> if thus for the <hi>bramble,</hi> what for the <hi>Olive?</hi> if thus for <hi>perſecutors</hi> of the Faith, what for the <hi>defendors</hi> of it? O pray for the peace and proſperity of ſuch, they ſhall proſper that doe it. Pitie it is but that mans tongue ſhould for ever cleave unto the rooſe of his mouth, that lives un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>der a gracious and religious government, and yet ſayes not ſo much as, God ſave the King, and ſo our laſt tranſlation renders it, and departs not from the originall, for the Septuagint in ſeverall places renders the Hebrew word by <gap reason="foreign" resp="#OXF">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap>, which ſignifies to ſave.</p>
            <p>There is no <hi>King</hi> that can be ſaved by the mul<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>titude of an hoſt. I will not truſt in my how, nei<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther ſhall my ſword ſave me ſayes King David. Salvation belongs unto the Lord, he alone is the Maſter of the Salvation Office; <hi>I am, and beſides me there is no Saviour.</hi> And therefore the people did well to addreſſe their devotions to the God of <hi>Iſrael,</hi> for the King of <hi>Iſrael.</hi> For his arme of protection cannot wither, nor his wings of ſalva<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion molt their feathers. Beſides, it is the obſer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vation
<pb n="30" facs="tcp:3424:18"/>of <hi>Ioſephus</hi> upon a danger which <hi>Titus</hi> eſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>caped when he came to view the Citie of Jeruſa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lem, <hi>Imperatorum pericula Deum curare,</hi>
               <note place="margin">De Bel. Jud. lib. 6. cap. 2.</note> that God takes the perſons and perills of Princes into his ſpeciall care and cogniſance. To God then they goe, and they goe for that which of all o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther things is moſt behoofefull, ſafety and ſalva<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion.</p>
            <p>There is a twofold ſalvation; one of the <hi>ſoule,</hi> the other of the <hi>body;</hi> one from <hi>ſinne,</hi> the other from <hi>danger;</hi> and Kings ſtand in neede of the firſt as well as others, and of the ſecond more then o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thers, ſo that ſalvation is that <hi>Vnu<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> neceſſarium,</hi> that one and onely thing which is neceſſary for them.</p>
            <p>
               <milestone type="tcpmilestone" unit="unspecified" n="1"/> As for the firſt, we are all <hi>Oves perditae,</hi> loſt ſheepe, the ſinne of our firſt parents was <hi>commune naufragium,</hi> an univerſall ſhipwracke: for in <hi>A<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dam</hi> all ſinned, yea the bleſſed virgin her ſelfe, for her ſoule rejoyced in God her Saviour. Now howſoever Kings in reſpect of <hi>Office,</hi> as they are <hi>Filii altiſsimi,</hi> the ſonnes of the moſt High are <hi>Tranſcendents:</hi> yet in reſpect of <hi>Nature,</hi> as they are <hi>Filii Adam,</hi> ſonnes of men, they are in the ſame <hi>predicament</hi> with others, <hi>i. e.</hi> ſinners. So that without ſalvation, <hi>Tophet</hi> is ordained of old, and prepared for the <hi>King,</hi> as well as for the people.</p>
            <p>
               <milestone type="tcpmilestone" unit="unspecified" n="2"/> As for the other kinde of ſalvation we all need it, but Kings eſpecially, becauſe their perſons are moſt expoſed unto dangers. They have <hi>Foes</hi> a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>broad, and <hi>Traitors</hi> at home. There be enemies to doe them violence, and ſonnes of wickedneſſe to hurt them. Hence is it that they walke in dan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ger,
<pb n="31" facs="tcp:3424:18"/>eate in danger, ſleepe in danger. <hi>Solomons</hi> bed muſt have threeſcore valiant men about it,<note place="margin">Cant. 3.7, 8.</note> of the valiant of Iſrael, every man having his ſword girt upon his thigh for feare in the night; and ſurely it is the mercy of the moſt High that they doe not miſcarry; ſo that nothing ſo fit for them as ſalva<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion, without which their lives will be troden downe, and their Honour laid in the duſt. Which our Church rightly underſtanding, uſes this <hi>Suf<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>frage</hi> in her <hi>Liturgy,</hi> O Lord ſave the King. And againe, in the prayer for the ſtate of Chriſts Church militant here on earth, praies in this man<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ner; We beſeech thee alſo to ſave and defend all Chriſtian Kings, Princes, and Governours, and eſpecially thy ſervant <hi>Charles</hi> our King; and now that we are come to him, we are come to the bu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſineſſe of the day: and as you have lent me your patience hitherto for a Survey of my text, ſo the <hi>Kings</hi> name may command it a little longer for a review, and application, which I ſhall diſpatch with all convenient brevitie, and ſo diſmiſſe you.</p>
            <p>No ſooner was our Sunne ſet in the death of King <hi>Iames</hi> of bleſſed memory, but it roſe againe in the happy inauguration of King <hi>Charles,</hi> ſo that no night followed, for <hi>Regem habemus,</hi> a King we have, and ſuch a one as the like is not among the people, nay ſuch an one I dare ſay as the like is not among the Kings of the earth; whether we reſpect the beauty of his perſon, or the graces of his foule: God hath bleſſed him with a ſtrong and healthfull conſtitution, a comely and Majeſti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>call
<pb n="32" facs="tcp:3424:19"/>preſence, an active and a vigorous body; and yet this is is but the Cabinet, the jewells that are lockt up in it are of ineſtimable value.</p>
            <p>As for his <hi>Humility,</hi> you may read it in his ap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>parell, eſpecially in the paſſages of theſe times, wherein he hath condeſcended as low to accom<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>modate cauſleſſe diſcontentments, and to remove offences taken, not given, as the reſpects of Maje<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſty would well ſuffer.</p>
            <p>As for his <hi>Piety,</hi> I challenge envy and malice it ſelfe to ſpeake their worſt. Is he not conſtant to his devotions, and reverent in them? Hath he deſired or indeavoured any thing more then a <hi>Conformity</hi> and <hi>Vniformity</hi> in Gods Service, that there might bee but <hi>via una,</hi> and <hi>cor unum,</hi> one way, and ſo one heart? Hath he not been zealous of the glory of God, and the publike places of his worſhip? If I ſhould hold my peace, theſe ſtones would ſpeake, I meane the ſtones that are brought to this Temple, to beautifie and vindi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cate it from a long and intolerable prophanation.</p>
            <p>As for his <hi>Clemency,</hi> doe we not all ſit under our owne Vines, and cate the fruit of them with<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>out any trembling, or palpitation, leſt we ſhould be arreſted with the meſſage of death or confiſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cation? Hath he inflicted any puniſhments but ſuch, as the offence impartially conſidered, <hi>mercy</hi> it ſelfe might have beene both the <hi>Iudge</hi> and <hi>Exe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cutioner?</hi> Or to expreſſe it in his owne royall language; Hath he not now for a long time toge<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther endeavoured by all calme and faire waies to appeaſe the diſorders, and tumultuous carriages,
<pb n="33" facs="tcp:3424:19"/>raiſed by ſome evill affected perſons, and fomen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted by ſome factious and turbulent ſpirits? and now that his patience is abuſed, and the ſword in his hand, doth he not call God and the world to witneſſe that he is forced and conſtrained there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>to? A King then we have, and ſuch a King as this, ſhew me a better among the people. I may ſay of him and the people, as the Epigram<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>matiſt does of <hi>Trajane</hi> and the <hi>Senate;</hi>
               <note place="margin">Mart. lib. 11. Epig. 5.</note> 
               <hi>Moribus hic viv at principis, ille ſuis:</hi> Let them live after his manners, and he after his owne. And if it be thus, how much are they to blame, who (though <hi>rebus ſic ſtantibus,</hi> they dare not raile at the King as <hi>Shimei</hi> did, or throw ſtones at him) yet in their Sermons, Conferences, Libels, and Pamphlets they miſ-interpret his actions, for his piety with them is Popery and Innovation, his clemency with them is cruelty and perſecution. And thus the people are brought into a diſlike and deteſta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion of the preſent government, and both the <hi>Per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſon</hi> and <hi>Authority</hi> of the King cunningly undermi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ned. If the Serpent can but buzze a jealouſie and ſuſpition into the heads of our firſt Parents that God envies their happineſſe, the Apple will goe downe without chewing. If <hi>Abſalom</hi> can poſſeſſe the people that juſtice is not adminiſtred, nor mat<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ters well carried, it is an eaſie matter to ſteale a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>way their hearts from their Allegiance to his Fa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther. And well it is that the holy Ghoſt gives it no better a title then ſtealth, for it is a theft of the higheſt nature; they rob not a private man, but a <hi>King;</hi> and that not of his Plate, his Jewels, or
<pb n="32" facs="tcp:3424:20"/>
               <gap reason="duplicate" extent="1 page">
                  <desc>〈1 page duplicate〉</desc>
               </gap>
               <pb n="33" facs="tcp:3424:20"/>
               <gap reason="duplicate" extent="1 page">
                  <desc>〈1 page duplicate〉</desc>
               </gap>
               <pb n="34" facs="tcp:3424:21"/>apparell, but of the <hi>
                  <gap reason="illegible" resp="#OXF" extent="1+ letters">
                     <desc>•…</desc>
                  </gap>ts</hi> of the people, and con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſequently they rob him of the <hi>Armes</hi> of his peo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ple, of the <hi>purſes</hi> of his people, of the <hi>prayers</hi> of his people, and make him as much as in them lies <hi>Lodovicus <gap reason="illegible" resp="#OXF" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>i<gap reason="illegible" resp="#OXF" extent="1+ letters">
                     <desc>•…</desc>
                  </gap>,</hi>
               <note place="margin">Lewes no bo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>die.</note> as ſometimes an Emperour of Germany was called; and for this ſtealth was <hi>Ab<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſalom</hi> juſtly and deſervedly hanged. And <hi>Solomon</hi> copied out this leſſon from his ruine; <hi>My ſon, ſeare God,</hi>
               <note place="margin">Prov. 24.22, 22.</note> 
               <hi>and the King, and meddle not with them that are given to change, for their calamity ſhall riſe ſuddenly, and who knowes the <gap reason="illegible" resp="#OXF" extent="1+ letters">
                     <desc>•…</desc>
                  </gap> of them both?</hi> Let as then, ſeeing we have a <hi>King,</hi> rejoyce in him; and ſeeing we have ſuch a <hi>King</hi> as the like is not, re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>joyce, yea I ſay againt rejoyce. Let our joy be as great, and as full as we can make it. For the bleſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſing is great, and ought to be celebrated with as great <hi>ſolemnity</hi> as is poſſible.</p>
            <p>And that our joy may not be as the crackling of thornes under a pot, but long and laſting; let us not only rejoyce in him, but pray for him. Pray for his life, <hi>Vivat Rex,</hi> let the King live; Let the ſoule of our Lord <hi>be bound up in the bandie of life;</hi>
               <note place="margin">1 Sam. 25.29.</note> 
               <hi>but as for the ſoules of his enemies, ſting them out O God, as out of the middle of a ſting. Prolong O God the Kings life,</hi>
               <note place="margin">Pſal. 61.6, 7.</note> 
               <hi>and his yeares as many generati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ons; Let him abide before thee for ever: O prepare thy loving mercy, and faithfulneſſe, that they may preſerve him.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>And as for his life, ſo pray alſo for his proſpe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rity. <hi>Sit Rex f<gap reason="illegible" resp="#OXF" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>lix,</hi> let the King proſper and flou<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>riſh. <hi>Give him O Lord the deſire of his heart, and de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ny him not the requeſt of his lips; prevent him with
<pb n="35" facs="tcp:3424:21"/>the bleſsings of goodneſſe and ſet a crown of pure gold upon his head: Let his glory be great in thy ſalvation. Honour and Majeſty doe them lay upon him:</hi>
               <note place="margin">Pſalme. 2.<gap reason="illegible" resp="#OXF" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>.</note> 
               <hi>give him everlaſting felicitie, and make him glad with the joy of thy co<gap reason="illegible" resp="#OXF" extent="1+ letters">
                     <desc>•…</desc>
                  </gap>enance. As for his enemies,</hi>
               <note place="margin">Pſal. 132.18.</note> 
               <hi>clothe them with ſhame, but upon himſelfe let his Crowne flouriſh. Good <gap reason="illegible" resp="#OXF" extent="1+ letters">
                     <desc>•…</desc>
                  </gap>ke have be with his honour, and let him ride on proſperouſly, that they that hate him may bow before him, and lick up the <gap reason="illegible" resp="#OXF" extent="1+ letters">
                     <desc>•…</desc>
                  </gap>ſt of his fe<gap reason="illegible" resp="#OXF" extent="1+ letters">
                     <desc>•…</desc>
                  </gap>e.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>And becauſe both theſe depends upon the ſafe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ty of his Perſon; Let us pray alſo, <hi>Domine ſalvum fac Regem,</hi> God ſave the King. And never was this prayer more ſeaſonable, for Lord <hi>how are they increaſed that trouble him, many they are that riſe up againſt him! They that have eaten of his bread, have lift up their heeles againſt him:</hi>
               <note place="margin">Pſal. 83.2.5.</note> 
               <hi>His enemies make a tumult, and they that hate him have lift up their heads, they have conſulted together againſt him with one conſent, and are confederate</hi> (or, as the word ſignifies) <hi>entred into Covenant againſt him. Be thou therefore O Lord a ſhield for him,</hi>
               <note place="margin">Pſal. 3.3.</note> 
               <hi>his glory and the lifter up of his head:</hi>
               <note place="margin">Pſal. 20.1.2.</note> 
               <hi>Heare him O Lord in the day of trouble, the name of the God of Iacob de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fend him; ſend him help from his Sanctuary, and ſtrengthen him out of Zion.</hi>
               <note place="margin">Pſal. 91.4.</note> 
               <hi>Defend him under thy wings, and let him be ſafe under thy feathers, let thy faithfulneſſe and truth be his ſhield, and buckler.</hi>
               <note place="margin">Pſal. 121.7, 8.</note> 
               <hi>Pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſerve him from all evill, preſerve his going out and his comming in from this time forth, and even for ever<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>more.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <hi>But as for his enemies, deſtroy them O God, let them fall by their owne counſels; caſt them out in the
<pb n="36" facs="tcp:3424:22"/>multitude of their tranſgreſsions, for they have rebel<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>led againſt him.</hi>
               <note place="margin">Pſal. 3.10.</note> 
               <hi>Let them melt and conſume away as the fat of Lambes.</hi>
               <note place="margin">Pſal. 83. Deut. 33.11.</note> 
               <hi>Make them as a wheele, and as the ſtubble before the winde. Smite thor<gap reason="illegible" resp="#OXF" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>w the loines of them that riſe againſt him, that they riſe not again. Beate downe his foes before his face, and plague them that hate him, and let him ſee his deſire upon his ene<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mies. So we thy people, and ſheep of thy paſture will give thee thankes for ever: we will ſhew forth thy praiſe to all generations.</hi>
            </p>
            <trailer>FINIS.</trailer>
         </div>
      </body>
      <back>
         <div type="imprimatur">
            <p>Imprimatur</p>
            <closer>
               <signed>THO: WYKES.</signed>
               <dateline>
                  <date>March 28. 1639.</date>
               </dateline>
            </closer>
            <pb facs="tcp:3424:22"/>
         </div>
      </back>
   </text>
</TEI>
